A Finding Aid to the William Mills Ivins Papers, 1878-1964, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Ivins Family Papers, circa 1878-1964; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; (Boxes 16-20; 4.5 linear ft.)
  - William M. Ivins, Sr., 1885-1924; 5.9; Archival Resource Key
    - Letters from William M. Ivins, Jr. from Harvard, 1897-1901; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Letters from William M. Ivins, Jr. from European Trip, 1901-1902; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Letters from Relatives, 1885-1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Biographical Notes, circa 1891-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Clippings, circa 1891-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1891-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Estate Correspondence, 1914-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 11)
- Photographs, circa 1890-1940; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; (Boxes 20-21; 1.5 linear ft.)
  In addition to portraits of family members this series includes interior and exterior views of homes, and pictures of friends and events.
  The series is organized into three subseries:
  6.1: Family Photographs, circa 1890-1905
  6.2: Photographs of Architecture by WMI, Jr., circa 1930-1940
  6.3: Miscellaneous Photographs, undated
  - Family Photographs, circa 1890-1905; 6.1; Archival Resource Key
    The Ivins Family photographs represent many processes from tintypes to silver gelatin prints. A number were taken by accomplished amateur photographer Emma Yard Ivins of her children, circa 1890-1905; a few of her children are purported to be the work of Gertrude Kasebier (possibly an acquaintance of Emma Yard Ivins?).
    Family photographs folders are labelled with the name of an individual or family, and arranged alphabetically; within each folder, photographs are arranged in rough chronological order. Portraits of individuals are filed by name and group shots are filed by the name of the family; childhood pictures are filed under the parents' family. (For example, pictures of Emma Yard Ivins as a child are filed under the name Yard and any group shots she appears in will be found under the name James S. and Adaline Swift Yard Family; group shots of her after marriage are included with the pictures of the William M. Jr. and Emma Yard Ivins Family).
    Photographs of William M. Ivins, Jr., and the Florence Wyman family include their New York City apartment, summer house in Westport, Conn., and their Woodbury, Conn. home in addition to photographs of them with friends Bryson Burroughs, Naum Gabo, Walter Hauser, A. Hyatt Mayor, Peyton Rous, Rudolph Ruzicka, Mahonri Young, and unidentified.
    - Ivins, Barbara (1913-), circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 12-13)
    - Ivins, Emma Yard (1857-1940), circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 14-15)
      (includes Yard Family home, Freehold, N.J.)
    - Ivins, Florence Wyman (1881-1948), circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 16-18)
      (includes photos of illustrations by FWI)
    - Ivins, Katharine (c. 1888-), circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 19)
    - Ivins, Margaret [Holmes] (1882-1954), circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 20)
    - Ivins, Sarah Mills (1832-1914), circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 21)
    - Ivins, William M., Jr. (1881-1961), circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 22-23)
    - Ivins, William M., Jr. and Florence Wyman Family, circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 24-33)
    - Ivins, William M., Sr. (1851-1915), circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 34)
    - Ivins, William M., Sr. and Emma Yard Family, circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 35-37)
      (including views of The Hut and The Breezes, Narragansett Pier, R.I.)
    - Mills, William T. (1811-), circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 38)
    - Wyman, Loraine (-1937), circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 39)
    - Yard, James Sterling (1826-1900) and Adaline Swift (1837-1912) Family (1826-1912), circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 40)
    - Yard, Mary Sterling (1805-1863), circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 41)
    - Unidentified People, circa 1890-1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 42-43)
  - Architecture Photographs, circa 1930-1940; 6.2; Archival Resource Key
    Architecture photographs mainly consist of photographs of colonial architecture, apparently taken by William M. Ivins circa 1930-1940. These are unidentified, except for location, and arranged by state. Also included are a few scenes of Europe from the same period, featuring buildings.
    - Europe, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 44-45)
    - Connecticut, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 46)
    - Maryland, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 47)
    - Massachussetts, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 48)
    - New Hampshire, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - New York, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Pennsylvania, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Rhode Island, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - South Carolina (Charleston), circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 5-7)
    - Vermont, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Virginia, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified locations [New England and elsewhere], circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 10-11)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated; 6.3; Archival Resource Key
    Miscellaneous photographs include those used as illustrations for How Prints Look and pictures of the Alberti Model for On the Rationalization of Sight (which may have been used to illustrate other writings, as well). The subseries also includes additional subjects such as a view of the Swarthmore College campus [Barbara's alma mater] and painting conservation [Metropolitan Museum of Art?].
    - Illustrations for How Prints Look, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 12-15)
    - Alberti Model, illustration for On the Rationalization of Sight, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous Subjects, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 17)
- Oversize Material, 1897-1950; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; (1 OV folder)
  - St. Paul's School Diploma, July 9, 1897; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 22)
  - Harvard College Diploma, June 27, 1901; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 22)
  - Columbia College School of Law Diploma, June 12, 1907; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 22)
  - Yale University, Honorary Doctorate Diploma, Nov. 14, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 22)
  - St. Paul's School, achievement award, July 9, 1897; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 22)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, honorary fellow, May 20, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 22)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, fellow, May 1, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 22)
  - U.S. Passport, September 24, 1901; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 22)